<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<kiln:root xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1"
           xmlns:kiln="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/kiln/ns/1.0"
           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
           xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

  <kiln:parent>
    <xi:include href="base.xml" />
  </kiln:parent>

  <kiln:child>
    <kiln:block name="title">
      <i18n:text>Factions</i18n:text>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="page-header">
      <div class="row">
        <div class="small-8 small-centered columns text-center">
          <h1 id="site-name"><a href="inscriptions/">Circus Factions in the Eastern Empire</a></h1>
        </div>
      </div>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="content-section">
      <main>
        <div class="row">
          <div class="small-8 small-centered columns">
            <p class="text-center">A corpus of the epigraphic evidence</p>
            <p class="text-center">Charlotte Roueché</p>
            <p class="text-center"><a href="inscriptions/"><img alt="FactionEphesos16" title="FactionEphesos16" src="{$kiln:assets-path}/images/FactionEphesos16.jpg"/></a></p>
            

              <p>
                A collection of currently known inscribed references to the Circus Factions in the eastern empire, beyond Constantinople, was first made in 1966 by 
                Α. Christophilopoulou; Alan Cameron then developed this in an Appendix to his 1976 study, <i>Circus Factions</i>. An expanded list was presented in 
                2021 by Roueché for a publication in memory of Alan Cameron 
                (for all these see further <a target="_blank" href="concordances/bibliography/">Bibliography/Concordance</a>).
These publications were simple assemblies or lists of texts, without the opportunity to present them in context. The aim of this article is to explore 
the benefits of online publication for a presentation of this kind. The material can, of course, be presented in full, with detailed descriptions of each of the 80 texts 
identified. In most cases it allows for illustration of those texts. Perhaps more importantly, it supports the categorisation of the items in various ways, which may help us 
to greater understanding of their function and significance.
            </p>
            <p> Cameron presented the items 
              by geographical area: but this form of presentation - imposed by a list in analogue form - perhaps obscures other differentiating 
              features. For the <b>geographic</b> distribution see Index of <a target="_blank" href="indices/epidoc/findspot.html">Findspots</a>. 
              To some extent the distribution reflects the intensity of study in certain areas: 
              there is for example a great deal of material from the well-excavated sites of Aphrodisias and Ephesus, and 80 texts come from only 30 locations. 
              Of those, only 7 had hippodromes; but this simply demonstrated, as Cameron showed, that interest in the factions spread far beyond the hippodrome.</p> 
            
            <p>Out of 80 texts the majority (50) have been recorded in situ, from sites which were not overlaid by further development after the seventh century. 

The <b>locations</b> can therefore be examined: see <a target="_blank" href="search/">Search</a>, under Monument Type. Many of the locations (27) are in auditoria, 
              as might be expected, or in streets, stairways and colonnades (16), where they may reflect the involvement of the factions in public ceremonial activities. 
              But some are found in a domestic context - and four are associated with churches.</p>
            
            <p>The <b>texts</b> can be analysed by type: see <a target="_blank" href="search/">Search</a>, under Text Type. Three people are identified by their factional 
              loyalties in their epitaphs; there are also 11 place 
              inscriptions. Three-quarters - 60 - are acclamations, 
              49 of which are calls for victory, 
              Νικᾷ ἡ τύχη.  Of these 6 also include the fortune of the emperor(s),  
              (7, 8, 9, 11, 14, 15), and two the fortune of the city (35, 55). Those seem clearly to have a public -?official - function; 
              Some acclamations, however, are clearly private - for example on a comb (75), or a pithos (61). 
              </p>
            
            <p>Whether a text can be understood as public/official or private/unofficial is therfore sometimes indicated by its <b>support</b> 
              (see <a target="_blank" href="search/">Search</a>, under Support Object Type. Of the place inscriptions 9 mark seating in an auditorium - 
              which might mark official or unofficial allocation.
            ; . more to add </p>
            
            <p>Execution?</p>
              

            
            </div>
            </div>
        
      </main>
    </kiln:block>
  </kiln:child>
</kiln:root>
