<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<kiln:root xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1"
           xmlns:kiln="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/kiln/ns/1.0"
           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
           xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

  <kiln:parent>
    <xi:include href="base.xml" />
  </kiln:parent>

  <kiln:child>
    <kiln:block name="title">
      <i18n:text>Factions</i18n:text>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="page-header">
      <div class="row">
        <div class="small-8 small-centered columns text-center">
          <h1 id="site-name"><a href="inscriptions/">Circus Factions in the Eastern Empire</a></h1>
        </div>
      </div>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="content-section">
      <main>
        <div class="row">
          <div class="small-8 small-centered columns">
            <p class="text-center">A corpus of the epigraphic evidence</p>
            <p class="text-center">Charlotte Roueché</p>
            <p class="text-center"><a href="inscriptions/"><img alt="FactionEphesos16" title="FactionEphesos16" src="{$kiln:assets-path}/images/FactionEphesos16.jpg"/></a></p>
            

              <p>The aim of this publication is to present all currently known inscribed references to the Circus Factions in the eastern empire, beyond Constantinople, in the fullest possible form. 
              A collection of this kind was first made in 1966 by Α. Christophilopoulou; Alan Cameron then developed this in an Appendix to his 1976 study, 

              <i>Circus Factions</i>. An expanded list was presented in 2021 by Roueché for a publication, in memory of Alan Cameron
                (see further <a target="_blank" href="concordances/bibliography/">Bibliography/Concordance</a>).

            </p>
            <p>The collections named above were simple assemblies of texts, without the opportunity to present them in context. Cameron presented the items 
              by geographical area: for the geographic distribution see Index of <a target="_blank" href="indices/epidoc/findspot.html">Findspots</a>. To some extent this refects the intensity of study in certain areas: 
              there is for example a great deal of material from the well-excavated sites of Aphrodisias and Ephesus. But this form of presentation perhaps obscures other differentiating 
              features. 
              Out of 77 texts the majority (57) have been recorded in situ, from sites which were not overlaid by further development after the seventh century. 

              The locations can therefore be examined: see <a target="_blank" href="search/">Search</a>, under Monument Type. Many of the locations (27) are in auditoria, 
              as might be expected, or in streets, stairways and colonnades (14), where they may reflect the involvement of the factions in public ceremonial activities. 
              But some are found in a domestic context - and four are associated with churches.<!-- refer to monument type --></p>

            
            </div>
            </div>
        
      </main>
    </kiln:block>
  </kiln:child>
</kiln:root>
