<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Discussion</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="text">
                
               <p>
                A collection of currently known inscribed references to the Circus Factions in the eastern empire, beyond Constantinople, was first made by 

                Αnastasia Christophilopoulou (<ref target="../concordance/bibliography/christoph1966.html">Christophilopoulou, 1966</ref>); Alan Cameron then developed this in an Appendix to his 1976 study, 
                   <ref target="../concordance/bibliography/cameronCF.html"><hi rend="italic">Circus Factions</hi></ref>. 
                   An expanded list was presented in <ref target="../concordance/bibliography/roueche2021">Roueché: 2021</ref>. 

                   The numbering of this collection follows that in the 2021 article, with some additions.
These publications were simple assemblies or lists of texts, without the opportunity to present them in context. The aim of this article is to explore 
the benefits of online publication for a study of this kind. The material can, of course, be presented in full, with detailed descriptions of each of the 83 texts 
identified. In most cases it allows for illustration of those texts. Perhaps more importantly, it supports the categorisation of the items in various ways, which may help us 
to greater understanding of their function and significance.
            </p>
            <p> Cameron presented the items 
              by geographical area: but this form of presentation - imposed by a list in analogue form - perhaps obscures other differentiating 
              features. For the <emph>geographic</emph> distribution see Index of <ref target="../indices/epidoc/findspot.html">Findspots</ref>. 
              To some extent the distribution reflects the intensity of study in certain areas: 
              there is for example a great deal of material from the well-excavated sites of Aphrodisias and Ephesus, and 83 texts come from only 30 locations. 
              Of those, only seven had hippodromes; but this simply demonstrated, as Cameron showed, that interest in the factions spread far beyond the hippodrome. 
              Indexing 
            makes it possible to see the variations in <emph>terminology</emph> and epithets used of the factions - and shows examples of the Reds as well as the Blues and Greens: 
             see Index of <ref target="../indices/epidoc/organisations.html">Organisations</ref></p> 
            
            <p>Out of 83 inscriptions the great majority (68) have been recorded in situ, from sites which were not overlaid by further development after the seventh century. 

The <emph>locations</emph> can therefore be examined: see <ref target="../search/">Search</ref>, under Monument Type. Many of the locations (30) are in auditoria, 
              as might be expected, or in streets, stairways and colonnades (16), where they may reflect the involvement of the factions in public ceremonial activities. 
              But some are found in a domestic context - and three - two acclamations and a prayer - are found in churches (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions023">23</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions065">65</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions068">68</ref>, with also perhaps <ref type="inscription" n="Factions061">61</ref>).</p>
            
            <p>The texts can be analysed by <emph>type</emph>: see <ref target="../search/">Search</ref>, under Text Type. Three people are identified by their factional 
              loyalties in their epitaphs; there are also 13 place 
              inscriptions. But three-quarters - 61 - are acclamations, 
              52 of which invoke fortune, 49 calling for the victory of fortune, 
              Νικᾷ ἡ τύχη.  Of these six also include the fortune of the emperor(s)  
              (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions007">7</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions008">8</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions009">9</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref> 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions014">14</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions015">15</ref>), and two the fortune of the city (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions035">35</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions055">55</ref>). Those seem clearly to have a public -
              ?official - function; 
              while some acclamations are clearly private/domestic - for example on a comb (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions075">75</ref>), or a pithos (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions061">61</ref>). 
                 There is also probably more material to be discovered. In particular the identification of acclamations 
            presented as monograms has revealed more texts  (currently nine examples): and such monograms, being hard to interpret, 
                are likely to have been under-reported. 
              </p>
            
            <p>There are further examples of texts whose function is indicated by their <emph>support</emph> 
              (see <ref target="../search/">Search</ref>, under Support Object Type). 11 acclamations are on seating - 
              which might mark official or unofficial allocation; eight other seats have place inscriptions. We can reasonably see both acclamations and place inscriptions on seats as serving a similar purpose, 
              of marking out seating for a group. Four place inscriptions and eight acclamations are on column shafts; 
              this is not unusual for place inscriptions, although it is sometimes unclear exactly what space they are defining. Their function may of course vary, 
              but in many cases an acclamation, or a place inscription, can indicate the location of a group at the time of a public event 
              (see <ref target="https://zenon.dainst.org/Record/001007365">Roueché: 1999</ref>). The two texts on a column at Oxyrhynchus (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions076">76</ref>) now unfortunately lost, 
                may illustrate this: the "place of the Blues" may 
              indicate where they stood on such an occasion, and the acclamation for Phocas may be what they then performed. It would be dangerous to interpret this, 
              as some have done, as evidence of a special relationship between the emperor and the faction; 
              it is entirely possible that there was a place of the Greens on another column, with 
              a similar acclamation. To be acclaimed by both factions was a far greater expression of power and stability than to be aligned with only one. I 
              believe that we can see 
              a similar arrangement, balancing acclamations by the two major factions, on the "Gate of Hadrian" at Ephesus, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref>, 
                with <ref target="https://zenon.dainst.org/Record/001007365">Roueché (1999)</ref>, no.7. Similarly at Aphrodisias acclamations for two factions are found either 
                side of the acclamation of the city (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">35</ref>).
            </p>
            <p>Another significant support is on the elements of a gateway. At Ephesus acclamations marked three official points of entry 
                (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions007">7</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions008">8</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref>) and another is on an element 
              of an entrance now lost (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions013">13</ref>). Acclamations at Aphrodisias also mark a point of entry (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions033">33</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions034">34</ref>); while these appear relatively public and formal, and can easily be associated with ceremonials for an adventus, another 
                acclamation in a doorway (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions036">36</ref>) seems simply to reserve a room for the Greens with an invocation of good fortune. 
            Another group, from Syria, are all on lintel blocks, three apparently in domestic buildings (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions063">63</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions064">64</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions066">66</ref>) and one, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions065">65</ref>, over an entrance into a church. These would seem to be 
            invocations of good fortune at the point of entry, in the tradition of the 'épigraphie des linteaux' characteristic of the area, perhaps more than expressions of support for a colour.</p>
            
            <p><emph>Execution</emph>?
            Traditional scholarship for many years saw such texts as insignificant, both because of their apparently frivolous content, and also because of their script; they were often classified as miscellaneous, 
            or with the rather unclear designation of graffiti, applied both to content and to form. We have a better understanding now of the role of acclamations, and 
            the study of late antique epigraphy has helped us appreciate styles of inscription that may have seemed inferior or casual. 
            Some texts are clearly the work of a mason with a chisel, even if the alignment is inelegant: 
            a striking example is the acclamations for Albinus at Aphrodisias, <ref target="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/iAph040021.html">IAph2007 4.21</ref>. Some are also in prominent 
                and public positions, such as those in the streets of Ephesus. The manner of inscribing is 
            clearly important: see <ref target="../search/">Search</ref>, under Execution Technique. 
            But whether an inscription can be understood as public/official or private/unofficial remains difficult in many cases. I have identified 43 texts as Inscribed/chiselled, and 
            another 32 as scratched/graffito: but in several cases I am far from sure of the appropriate description. It may be that we need 
            further descriptive categories for defining various forms of non-standard execution.</p>  
                <p>
                With all these tools of analysis, therefore, interpretation of some texts and their function 
             remains difficult. A good example is provided by <ref type="inscription" n="Factions035">35</ref>, a group of acclamations for the two factions and the city. The content therefore suggests a 
            relatively formal function. The location is challenging, because they are cut on the face of three adjacent column bases, and thus fairly close to the ground; the 
            execution is in complex and elegant letters, but very lightly cut with a thin point. Their status and function must therefore remain uncertain. Similarly <ref type="inscription" n="Factions038">38</ref>, 
            while apparently formal in content, does not appear so in execution. All of this makes it particularly valuable to be able to provide illustrations of the majority of these texts.</p>
                
             
                
                <p>As often, encoding the inscriptions has enforced a more careful approach to their categorisation. The evidence which emerges is far more complex than the simple mention of a faction. 
                    There are texts which express ownership by a faction or members of a faction - whether buildings in Tyre and Gerasa (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions056">56</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions062">62</ref>), a dressing-room at Aphrodisias (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions036">36</ref>) or the comb of Helladia (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions075">75</ref>). 
                There are texts apparently associated with ceremonial activity, as described above. There are texts which may simply be private annotations, invoking good fortune - 
                as on a pithos (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions061">61</ref>) or an amphora fragment (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions001a">1a</ref>). In the past the first known examples 
                    of such texts tended to be over-interpreted. 
                    Alan Camerons's work helped to dispel some of the theories about the factions and their political or religious significance. We are now in a position to examine the range of inscribed texts 
                    which refer to the factions, and to distinguish between them. In some cases the value of association with the faction may be as an embodiment of fortune and victory, 
                    rather than practical partisanship. I would suggest that the 
                invocation of victorious fortune for a faction could be used as an invocation of such fortune for the individual or the community, in a formula acceptable in a Christian context 
                (see further <bibl><ptr target="roueche2021"/>Roueché: 2021</bibl>). 
                    Perhaps the man identified in his epitaph as a Blue (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions052">52</ref>) had 
                    simply associated himself with a victorious entity whose good fortune he might have hoped to share. A modern parallel may be the ubiquitous football shirt, 
                    worn by people of all ages and cultures; 
                    the wearer is associating himself with the successful player whose number is on the shirt, partly as an expression of support, 
                    but perhaps more to invoke similar success in life for himself.  </p>
                
                <p>An epitaph, of course is clearly personal. 
                    The challenge which this material seems to me to present is the difficulty of assessing the status of particular texts, on the long spectrum between an offical statement by the community, 
                    and the private scribble of an individual, or something on a long spectrum in between. One aim of this article is simply to make these materials richly available, and to draw some conclusions: 
                    but perhaps more important is to raise more questions, both about this particular category of texts, 
                    and also about the broader range of informal inscriptions. Richer illustration is making more and more of such texts available: 
                    do we need to build an appropriate shared vocabulary with which to describe and then discuss such materials? 
                    The rich possibilities for collaboration which are created by online publication make it more important than ever for us to develop and refine agreed vocabularies; 
                    one aim of this article is to demonstrate how useful such vocabularies might be.</p>
              

            
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
