<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Discussion</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="text">
                
               <p>
                A collection of currently known inscribed references to the Circus Factions in the eastern empire, beyond Constantinople by 
                Α. Christophilopoulou <bibl><ptr target="christoph1966"/>Christophilopoulou (1966)</bibl>; Alan Cameron then developed this in an Appendix to his 1976 study, 
                   <bibl><ptr target="cameron1976"/>Circus Factions</bibl>. An expanded list was presented in <bibl><ptr target="roueche2021"/>Roueché (2021)</bibl>. 
                   The numberinfg of this collection follows that in the 2021 article, with some additions.
These publications were simple assemblies or lists of texts, without the opportunity to present them in context. The aim of this article is to explore 
the benefits of online publication for a presentation of this kind. The material can, of course, be presented in full, with detailed descriptions of each of the 80 texts 
identified. In most cases it allows for illustration of those texts. Perhaps more importantly, it supports the categorisation of the items in various ways, which may help us 
to greater understanding of their function and significance.
            </p>
            <p> Cameron presented the items 
              by geographical area: but this form of presentation - imposed by a list in analogue form - perhaps obscures other differentiating 
              features. For the <hi rend="b">geographic</hi> distribution see Index of <ref target="indices/epidoc/findspot.html">Findspots</ref>. 
              To some extent the distribution reflects the intensity of study in certain areas: 
              there is for example a great deal of material from the well-excavated sites of Aphrodisias and Ephesus, and 83 texts come from only 30 locations. 
              Of those, only 7 had hippodromes; but this simply demonstrated, as Cameron showed, that interest in the factions spread far beyond the hippodrome.</p> 
            
            <p>Out of 83 texts the majority (50) have been recorded in situ, from sites which were not overlaid by further development after the seventh century. 

The <hi rend="b">locations</hi> can therefore be examined: see <ref target="search/">Search</ref>, under Monument Type. Many of the locations (30) are in auditoria, 
              as might be expected, or in streets, stairways and colonnades (16), where they may reflect the involvement of the factions in public ceremonial activities. 
              But some are found in a domestic context - and four are associated with churches.</p>
            
            <p>The texts can be analysed by <hi rend="b">type</hi>: see <ref target="./search/">Search</ref>, under Text Type. Three people are identified by their factional 
              loyalties in their epitaphs; there are also 13 place 
              inscriptions. But three-quarters - 61 - are acclamations, 
              51 of which are calls for victory, 
              Νικᾷ ἡ τύχη.  Of these 6 also include the fortune of the emperor(s)  
              (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions007">7</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions008">8</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions009">9</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref> 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions014">14</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions015">15</ref>), and two the fortune of the city (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions035">35</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions055">55</ref>). Those seem clearly to have a public -
              ?official - function; 
              Some acclamations, however, are clearly private/domestic - for example on a comb (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions075">75</ref>), or a pithos (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions061">61</ref>,). 
              </p>
            
            <p>The function of a text is sometimes indicated by its <hi rend="b">support</hi> 
              (see <ref target="search/">Search</ref>, under Support Object Type). 11 acclamations are on seating - 
              which might mark official or unofficial allocation; 8 other seats have place inscriptions. Should we see both acclamations nd place inscriptions as serving a similar purpose, 
              of marking out seating for a group? Four place inscriptions and eight acclamations are on column shafts; 
              this is not unusual for place inscriptions, although it is sometimes unclear exactly what space they are defining. Their meaning may of course vary, 
              and I have argued that in some cases an acclamation, or a place inscription, may indicate the location of a group at the time of a public event 
              (<ref target="https://zenon.dainst.org/Record/001007365">Roueché: 1999</ref>). The two texts on a column at Oxyrhynchus (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions076">76</ref>) now unfortunately lost, 
                may indicate this: the "place of the Blues" may 
              indicate where they stood on such an occasion, and the acclamation for Phocas may be what they then performed. It would be dangerous to interpret this, 
              as some have done, as evidence of a special relationship between the emperor and the faction: 
              it is entirely possible that there was a place of the Greens on another column, with 
              a similar acclamation. To be acclaimed by both factions was a far greater expression of power and stability than to be aligned with only one; I 
              belive that we can see 
              a similar arrangement, balancing acclamations by the two major factions, on the "Gate of Hadrian" at Ephesus, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref>, 
                with <ref target="https://zenon.dainst.org/Record/001007365">Roueché (1999)</ref>, no.7.
            </p>
            <p>Another significant support is on the elements of a gateway. At Ephesus acclamations marked three official points of entry 
                (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions007">7</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions008">8</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions011">11</ref>) and another is on an elements 
              of an entrance now lost (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions013">13</ref>). Acclamations at Aphrodisias also mark a point of entry (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions033">33</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions034">34</ref>); while these appear relatively public and formal, another (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions038">38</ref>) seems much less so. 
            Another group, from Syria, are all on lintel blocks, three apparently in domestic buildins (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions063">63</ref>, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions064">64</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions066">66</ref>) and one, <ref type="inscription" n="Factions065">65</ref>, over an entrance into a church. These would seem to be 
            invocations of good fortune, in the tradition of the 'épigraphie des linteaux' characteristic of the area, perhaps more than expressions of support for a colour. This has led me to argue 
            that these texts may reflect, in some cases, a general wish to be associated with victory, perhaps even more than partisanship (see further <bibl><ptr target="roueche2021"/>Roueché 2021</bibl>)</p>
            
            <p><hi rend="b">Execution</hi>?
            Traditional scholarship for many years saw such texts as insignificant, both because of their apparently frivolous content, and also because of their script; they were often classified as miscellaneous, 
            or with the rather unclear designation of graffiti, applied both to content and to form. We have a better understanding now of the role of acclamations, and 
            the study of late antique epigraphy has helped us appreciate styles of inscription that may have seemed inferior or casual. 
            Some texts are clearly the work of a mason with a chisel, even if the alignment is inelegant 
            a striking example is the acclamations for Albinus at Aphrodisias, <ref target="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/iAph040021.html">IAph2007 4.21</ref>. The manner of inscribing is 
            clearly important: see <ref target="./search">Search</ref>, under Execution. Some are also in prominent and public positions, such as those in the streets of Ephesus. 
            But whether an inscription can be understood as public/official or private/unofficial remains difficult in many cases. I have identified 43 texts as Inscribed/chiselled, and 
            another 32 as scratched/graffito (see <ref target="search/">Search</ref>, under Execution Technique): but in several cases I am far from sure of the appropriate description. It may be that we need 
            further descriptive categories for defining various forms of non-standard execution. It is also likely that the interpretation of some texts and their function 
            remains difficult. A good example is provided by <ref type="inscription" n="Factions035">35</ref>, a group of acclamations for the two factions and the city. The content therefore suggests a 
            relatively formal function. The location is challenging, because they are cut on the face of three adjacent column bases, and thus relatively close to the ground; and the 
            execution is in complex and elegant letters, but very lightly cut with a thin point. Their status and function must therefore remain uncertain. Similarly <ref type="inscription" n="Factions038">38</ref>, 
            while apparently formal in content, does not appear so in execution. All of this makes it particularly valuable to be able to provide illustration of the majority of these texts.</p>
                
                <p>There is probably more to ne discovered. In particular the identification of acclamations presented as monograms (see <ref target="search/">Search</ref>, under Execution Technique) </p>
                
                <p>As often, encoding the inscriptions has enforced a more careful approach to their categorisation. The evidence which emerges is far more complex than the simple mention of a faction. 
                    There are texts which express ownership by a faction or members of a faction - whether buildings in Tyre and Gerasa (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions056">56</ref>, 
                <ref type="inscription" n="Factions062">62</ref>), a dressing-room at Aphrodisias (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions036">36</ref>) or the comb of Helladia (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions075">75</ref>). 
                There are texts apparently associated with ceremonial activity, as described above. There are texts which may simply be private annotations, invoking good fortune - 
                as on a pithos (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions061">61</ref>) or an amphora fragment (<ref type="inscription" n="Factions001a">1a</ref>). I would suggest that the 
                invocation of victorious fortune for a faction could also serve as an invocation of victorious fortune for the individual or the community, in a formula acceptable in a Christian context. 
                There is more to be discovered: in particular, the kinds of monograms</p>
              

            
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
